Guide to the Edgar R. Baker Papers 1926-2011 (bulk, 1940s-1969) MS 3156
New-York Historical Society
Edgar R. Baker papers
1926-2011 (bulk 1940s-1969)
New-York Historical Society
Baker, Edgar R. (Edgar Robey), 1920-1969
MS 3156
5 Linear feet in four record cartons and one flat box
The collection holds the papers of Time, Inc. executive Edgar R. Baker (1920-1969), especially as they relate to his almost two decades as head of Time's international unit, TIME-LIFE International, during its years of expansion from the mid-1940s to mid-1960s. The collection includes business and personal correspondence; subject files; speeches on U.S. foreign relations; photographs of business meetings, conferences, and social gatherings; and memorabilia from childhood school years to adulthood. An extensive set of carbon copies of Baker's business letters and memoranda from 1950 into the 1960s provides insight into Baker's leadership in confronting both internal challenges (performance of overseas offices and staff, expense management, revenue growth) and external obstacles (protectionist markets, government regulations, censorship) in expanding Time's global presence. Baker's personal letters to his wife and mother while traveling abroad, especially during his months-long trip in 1947, provide another angle of vision on the work of an international publisher seeking to extend American economic and policy interests globally in the post-World War II era.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series:
I. Outgoing Memos & Letters, Time Inc. (1950-1969)
II. Subject Files (1926-2011)
III. Correspondence, Personal (1942-1971)
IV. Photographs & Memorabilia (1940s-1960s)
Related Materials
N-YHS holds the extensive archives of Time Inc. Those records consist of over 50 record groups, which are cataloged individually and described more fully in individual finding aids. An overview of the Time Inc. archive can be found by following this link: Guide to the Time Inc. Records Overview
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edgar Baker's nephew, Josh Bowers, in 2019 and 2020.
Biographical / Historical
Edgar Robey Baker, Jr. (1920-1969) was an executive with TIME Inc. with responsibility for leading the company's international division during its expansion in the decades immediately after World War II.
Baker was born on October 16, 1920, in Washington, D.C. He attended public schools in Washington including Whittier elementary school, Paul Junior High School and Central High School. He earned an AB in Economics from George Washington University (GWU) in 1941, where he was a member of the honorary society Phi Beta Kappa. After some graduate studies, he worked as an economist for the U.S. government from 1942 to 1945 in the Department of Labor, Lend-Lease Administration, and Foreign Economic Administration. In 1944, Baker married Alice Newcomer of Winter Park, Florida, an aspiring journalist whom he had met at GWU.
In December 1945, Baker was hired by TIME Inc. as an assistant to the Managing Director of LIFE. In 1946, he was named General Manager of TIME's new operating division, TIME-LIFE International (TLI), reporting to C.D. Jackson. In 1949 Baker succeeded Jackson, who became Publisher of FORTUNE, and was promoted to Managing Director of TLI, becoming head of TIME Inc.'s international division with responsibility for its worldwide publishing operations. He reached executive rank in 1957, being elected a Vice President that year.
By the end of Baker's tenure at TLI in 1964, TIME's global presence had grown to include offices in 20 countries publishing 10 international editions, including some in languages other than English, with circulations of about 1.5 million each. Among these was a Spanish language version of LIFE and a Japanese language version of FORTUNE. He played a leadership role behind two significant TIME, Inc. initiatives: the 1955 Inter-American Investment Conference in New Orleans and the 1957 International Industrial Development Conference in San Francisco. He was a frequent conference speaker or panelist on topics concerning United States foreign relations and foreign trade in the postwar era. In 1959, Baker was a member of the small delegation to Poland headed by U.S. Secretary of Commerce Frederick H. Mueller.
Baker was based in TIME's New York headquarters, but he traveled often through Asia, Southeast Asia, Australia, Europe, and South and Central America, sometimes accompanied by his wife, Alice. In the midst of one such trip spanning the globe with Alice, in September 1963, Baker suffered a heart attack in Rome. He recovered and returned to the U.S. by ship in late 1963.
In early 1965, Baker was transferred from TLI, replaced by his lieutenant, Charles (Charley) Bear. In his new role as a Corporate Vice President and, in 1966, as Director of Research and Development, Baker was responsible for identifying new business lines and products for the diversification of TIME, Inc. In this role, Baker became involved with an educational joint venture with General Electric, TIME Inc.'s investment in film studio MGM, and the acquisition of book publisher Little, Brown, among others.
Beyond TIME Inc., Baker remained attached as an alumni to George Washington University, supporting their fundraising efforts. Politically, he was a liberal Democrat who was an early supporter of John F. Kennedy in the 1960 presidential campaign; as a result Baker was apparently in consideration for a foreign service role in the new administration. He was an avid baseball fan, especially of his hometown Washington Senators. He and Alice lived at 980 Fifth Avenue in New York and had a summer home in Sharon, Connecticut. On June 11, 1969, Baker died at the age of 48, reportedly of acute infectious hepatitis.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds the papers of Time, Inc. executive Edgar R. Baker (1920-1969), especially as they relate to his almost two decades as head of Time's international unit, TIME-LIFE International, during its years of expansion from the mid-1940s to mid-1960s. The collection includes business and personal correspondence; subject files; speeches on U.S. foreign relations; photographs of business meetings, conferences, and social gatherings; and memorabilia from childhood school years to adulthood.
An extensive set of carbon copies of Baker's business letters and memoranda from 1950 into the 1960s provides insight on Baker's leadership in confronting both internal challenges (staff performance, expense management, revenue growth) and external obstacles (protectionist markets, government regulation and censorship) in expanding Time's global presence. These files also hold documentation about Baker's planning of two conferences: the 1955 Inter-American Investment Conference in New Orleans and the 1957 International Industrial Development Conference in San Francisco.
Though the carbon copy files directly reflect Baker's business activities, Baker's related personal papers provide further context to some of these events. Subject files hold several of Baker's speeches to trade groups providing insight into his animating views on U.S. foreign relations and economic policy in the 1940s-1950s. His personal correspondence, written to his wife and mother while traveling abroad, provide another angle of vision on the work of an international publisher seeking to extend American economic and policy interests globally in the post-World War II era.
Further, while the memos, correspondence and subject files track TIME-LIFE International's, and Baker's, successes, the collection also provides a sense of the personal effort, stress, and cost of this success as glimpsed in letters with their suggestion of marital tensions, the business social settings with their attendant drinking and smoking depicted in the photographs, the get well letters in response to Baker's heart attack in 1963, and the 1969 condolence letters to his wife, Alice. The collection includes many of the obituaries and reminiscences of Baker, including a 1980 letter sent by Alice to Time historian Curt Prendergast reflecting on Edgar's career and achievements. Alice herself is well-represented in the collection, with letters to Edgar during his travels, in some photographs, and in various travel itineraries that combine Time business and personal leisure, all illustrating the essential, even expected, role of a supportive spouse to the success of a married executive.
Letters (correspondence); Memorandums.; Photographs.; Passports.; Report cards.; Speeches (documents); Business travel.; Businessmen.; International business enterprises.; Periodicals -- Publishing.; Publishers and publishing.; Inter-American Investment Conference (1955: New Orleans, La.) [611]; International Industrial Conference (1957: San Francisco, Calif.) [611]; Time, inc. -- History.; Time, inc. -- Management.
- Series I. Outgoing Memos & Letters, Time Inc., November 1950-1969; 1 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes Edgar Baker's files of carbon copies of his outgoing correspondence. The bulk of this correspondence is in connection with his Time, Inc business matters, though there are minor exceptions to this. Most of the correspondence dates from late 1950 to 1964, during the period in which Baker was General Manager and then Managing Director of TIME-LIFE International (TLI).
  Writing from New York to offices in London, Paris, Tokyo, Mexico City, and elsewhere, Baker's correspondence addresses a range of substantive issues concerning the international operation. These include business profitability, especially in the context of sales of advertising space and related ad rates; expense management, such as identifying alternative printing operation locations and establishing policies for travel and entertainment; market entry and publication launches, such as establishing a Spanish language edition, LIFE EN ESPANOL (1953) and opening offices in the Netherlands, India, and elsewhere; distribution, including focusing on the timing of delivery of the magazines to newsstands; and staff administration, including setting and enforcing sales force revenue quotas and other office performance measures, identifying housing arrangements and pension plan needs, and even considering plans for the safety of personnel in Paris should there be a military invasion (1951). While individual memos give insight into particular issues, the files also include Baker's overall business assessments of profit/loss, budgets, and the like; these are often copies of memos to Henry Luce and input for higher level reports to the Board and to stockholders.
  In addition to writing about internal TLI operations and business concerns, much of the correspondence is concerned with country-specific issues impacting or potentially impacting TLI's business prospects. Many of these relate to protectionist actions, such as discriminatory taxation (e.g., Canada) or outright bans on American magazines (e.g., Cuba's Bloque de la Prensa's (Press Block) attempts to suppress US magazine circulation). Other memos survey countries more generally, such as Australia, Mexico, and Venezuela. The files also hold extensive documentation concerning planning for the international conferences held in New Orleans (1955) and in San Francisco (1957).
  In 1965, with Baker's change in assignment to Vice President & Director of Corporate Development, most references to international business ends. These final folders hold fewer substantive documents, but there are several significant matters represented, including proposals from Baker for an educational joint venture with General Electric, purchase of New York Graphic Society, purchase of shares of MGM sufficient to claim Board representation, acquisition of the Newark Evening News, and the creation of a TIME-LIFE Films unit.
  Arrangement
  The series remains in its original order, which is chronological overall, though the content of each folder is reverse chronological.
  - Outgoing Correspondence Files, TIME-LIFE International (18 folders), 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
  - Outgoing Correspondence Files, Corporate (4 folders), 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1926-2011 (bulk, 1930s-1960s); 1.5 Linear feet
  The series, compiled by the processing archivist, brings together various files in the collection that have a subject orientation with different formats. The subject matter ranges from Baker's elementary school years in the 1920s-1930s through his career with Time Inc. in the 1940s-1960s and ends with the reminiscences following his death in 1969.
  Most of the files relate to Baker's career with Time Inc., especially with Time-Life International (TLI) from the mid-1940s until his transfer and promotion to corporate executive roles in 1965-1966. Files from the mid to late 1940s include documentation about the emerging vision for Time's global expansion. The growth of the business and Baker's career can be traced through the files, which includes press releases, Time Inc's in-house newsletter FYI, clippings, tearsheets, and some correspondence and memos. Two important events co-sponsored by Time that Baker was responsible for are well-represented in these files: the Inter-American Investment Conference held in New Orleans (1955) and the International Industrial Development Conference held in San Francisco (1957). Also in the files are the text of several remarks or speeches on foreign trade policy, economics and relations between the United States and Asia and elsewhere that were made by Baker to the Far East-America Council of Commerce and Industry, Export Managers Club of New York, and other such groups. Baker's trip to Poland in 1959 as part of a small delegation with the U.S. Secretary of Commerce is documented with Baker's notes on the trip and other material.
  The files from the mid to late 1960s, that is, after Baker was transferred out of the International Division, are sparser, but still hold several proposals for corporate acquisitions or initiatives from Baker to the Time Board or other executives. Baker's wife, Alice, traveled overseas with him at times and supported his work with duties as hostess to some events; her first-hand perspective on Baker and his contributions were documented in a 1980 letter to Time historian Curt Prendergast, and that is in these files.
  More specific information on the content of each file is provided in the container list. Patrons should be aware that many of the documents in this series suffered from water damage and rusting of staples and paper clips and so are often discolored, stiff or have other signs of damage; nonetheless, all but a few documents are readable.
  The series is arranged primarily in chronological order. Many of the files, such as those concerning Baker's education, remain as found by the processing archivist. Others had their content rearranged somewhat to form a more linear progression.
  - Boyhood School Years, 1926-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes Baker's report cards from elementary school, junior high school, and high school; National Honor Society card; Paul Junior High honor certificate (1934); program for Central High School commencement (1937); a few papers written by Baker (1937?); and documents related to a scholarship won to Washington & Lee University (eventually declined by Baker).
  - George Washington University Years (3 folders), 1938-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    Includes grade reports and transcripts; letters to Baker concerning school employment, scholarships, admissions to honor societies and to Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy (1942); three writings by Baker on foreign policy; several papers, exam answers, and notes for courses; booklets, programs, and certificates in connection with honor societies; and commencement program. There are also several clippings for 1940-42, especially from the campus newspaper "The Hatchet," many of which relate to Baker's elections to GWU's Student Congress as the Progressive Party candidate.
  - Early 1940s Miscellaneous, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes various writings by Baker: a published letter to the editor of the Washington Star expressing concern about a distortion in the paper of Senator George Norris's speech against peacetime conscription; a lengthy letter to the editor of the New York Times concerning the economic relationship beteen the U.S. and Great Britain (1945); two writings about post-war U.S. global economic matters; and a short piece of fiction(?) written by Baker (undated, likely 1940s or 1950s). There are also a few small newspaper clippings about the wedding of Baker and Alice Newcomer; employment-related communications from government agencies to Baker dating from prior to his joining Time Inc.; and an October 1944 letter to James W. Pope at Time Inc. from Baker relating to his eventual employment there, with his resume.
  - TLI. Project X (2 folders), 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    The documents relate to proposals and interest to launch foreign language edition(s) of TIME. Includes binder content of the proposal (likely 1945) with other documents that survey the origins of TLI and the early vision for international expansion.
  - TLI Matters, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes several telegrams to/from Baker in Calcutta, and copies of FYI and TIME (and a couple clippings) with summaries of Baker's worldwide trip. See also the Correspondence, Personal series for the many letters Baker wrote to his wife and other family members during this 1947 trip.
  - TLI Matters, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes press clippings about Baker's denials that TLI would receive government subsidies for overseas distribution; congratulatory note to Baker on the business's success; announcements about Baker's promotion to head of the International Division (and other organizational changes); a letter from Baker to Assistant Secretary of State George Allen responding to a constituent complaint about LIFE International using a photograph uncomplimentary to the U.S., and a few other documents.
  - Central High School. Certificate of Distinction, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Alumni award to Baker, with related documents.
  - TLI Matters, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes photographs, menu, and other documents for a dinner in London celebrating LIFE's first overseas printing operation (1950); programs for the United Nations American Public Relations Association Conference (1950) and the Institute on Brotherhood at Home and Abroad (1951), at which Baker was a panelist; roster of the Foreign Trade Club of Detroit and outline of Baker's remarks, titled "The Real Voice of America," delivered to the group (1951); and copies of FYI and other print matter.
  - TLI Matters (2 folders), 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    The first folder holds congratulatory letters, and related annoucements, to Baker for his promotion to Managing Director of TLI; and clippings and a transmittal to staff of the first issue of LIFE EN ESPANOL. The second folder holds a transcript of a radio broadcast interview of U.S. Senator Styles Bridges in which Baker is a co-interviewer asking about President Truman's seizure of the steel mills; a "first draft statement by the Committee on Foreign Investment and Economic Development"; and a galley print of Baker's remarks titled "The Carrot and the Stick," given to the Export Managers Club of New York, with related documents indicating it was also delivered to the World Trade Club of Denver.
  - TLI Matters, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes Baker's remarks delivered to Milwaukee export managers (July), to the Far East-America Council of Commerce and Industry on "The Climate of Business Opinion in Japan" (October), a "Los Angeles Speech" on U.S.-Asia relations (November), and a summary of panelist comments, including Baker, on "Asia's Challenge to Private Enterprise" (December); and documents related to other presentations by Baker, though not his remarks in those cases. The folder also holds some copies of FYI and clippings.
  - TLI. Inter-American Investment Conference, New Orleans (3 folders), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    Holds two memos from Baker to TLI salesmen about the purpose and content of the conference; publicity material; preliminary registration list (with attached list of attendee wives to be hosted at luncheons by Baker's wife, Alice); printed "Proceedings," which includes transcripts of the speakers' remarks; and pre- and post-conference clippings and other similar material. (See also Series I, years 1954-55, for extensive memos and letters from Baker concerning the conference planning.)
  - TLI Matters (3 folders), 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    The bulk of the material dates from 1955 with only a couple from 1956. The first folder holds news clippings, press releases, and remarks by Baker, all related to TLI's Japan operation, especially the opening in May of new offices in Tokyo's Sankei Kaikan building (several documents are in Japanese). The second folder holds mostly news clippings related to South America (several are in Spanish). The third folder holds Baker's brief remarks (possibly incomplete) as guest speaker at a class on foreign policy at Colgate in January and his later remarks at the Colgate Foreign Policy Conference in July; the folder also holds other documents related to Baker's presentations in other settings, though with no remarks here.
  - TLI. International Industrial Development Conference, San Francisco (3 folders), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
    Holds the conference materials (program, participant list and supplement, and facts and figures booklet); social program; publicity; personal items related to Baker's role at the conference (name tag, invitation), including a letter from Henry Luce to Baker with compliments; a preface by Baker for a book of proceedings (book not in collection); clippings; and a few other related documents.
  - TLI Matters (3 folders), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
    Includes announcements, clippings and congratulatory letters regarding Baker's promotion to Vice President; Baker's remarks to the Institute of Directors, London, with program, seating and table plan booklet, pen and pencil sketch of Baker at the podium, and clippings; menu and table plan for the dinner of the International Chamber of Commerce's British National Committee; a detailed memo concerning the financial status of the anticipated release of the movie "John Paul Jones" by Warner Brothers; a few thank you letters to Baker from employees; and news clippings (many in Spanish).
  - TLI Matters (2 folders), 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    Holds Baker's remarks made at the 21st Chicago World Trade Conference, with photograph, speaker name tag and ribbon, version of the speech as printed in "The Forwarder" as "Foreign Policy in the Space Age" and the version entered by Hubert Humphrey into the Congressional Record; Baker's remarks titled "What's Coming Up On the International Fronts?" made at the Economic Club of Detroit; statement by Baker before the U.S. Senate Appropriations Committee on the informational media guaranty program; rough draft of remarks on U.S.-Soviet relations; Baker's proposal to the Time, Inc. Board to form a subscription processing and distribution subsidiary in Mexico; and clippings (many in Spanish).
  - TLI. U.S. Department of Commerce Mission to Poland, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Baker was one of two representatives from outside government who were part of Commerce Secretary Frederick Mueller's 5 member delegation to Poland in November. Folder holds Baker's handwritten notes on the trip, some photographs (though most are severely water damaged), bilingual program/itinerary, guest list for reception of delegation, invitations, and visa application and authorization form.